When it comes to something
as life-and-death important
as what to feed ourselves
and our families,
we should rely not on
anecdotes, but on facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, we look at new research
that reveals why we should steer clear
of consuming chlorella and spirulina.
Here’s our first story.
Schizochytrium,
the type of algae
used to make
algae-based DHA supplements
is grown
under controlled conditions
and has been found
to be free of marine biotoxins.
The same can't be said
for blue-green algae products,
like AFA,
Aphanizomenon flos-aquae,
a blue-green algae harvested
from Klamath Lake in Oregon
and marketed
as a dietary supplement.
Studies have shown
this blue-green algae
can produce
significant levels
of cylindrospermopsin
and saxitoxin.
Cylindrospermopsin
is a liver toxin,
and saxitoxin
is a neurotoxin,
listed as a Schedule 1 substance
in the Chemical Weapons
Convention.
The first big exposé of AFA
was published in 2000,
with microcystin liver toxins
found in 85 of 87 samples,
72 percent exceeding
Oregon State's safety limits
of one part per million,
which is based on
an average adult
weighing 60 kg,
about 132 pounds,
and consuming
about 2 grams a day.
AFA has the toxigenic genes
that produce
these microcystins directly,
but when you're harvesting it
outdoors,
it's almost impossible
to avoid the presence
of other algae species
that can produce toxins too.
Since their release
on the market
and after some public inquiries
about adverse health effects
of these products,
the producers of the Klamath
Lake blue-green algae products
have repeatedly claimed
that their products are safe.
Well, okay, maybe not safe,
but at least
has toxin contamination
below the regulatory limit.
In 2018, dozens
of blue-green algae products
containing AFA were tested,
and about a quarter
were close to, or over,
the regulatory limit,
though only one
Klamath Lake powder
significantly exceeded the limit
at nearly three parts
per million.
But in 2020,
two AFA supplements
tested at closer to
50 parts per million.
At the recommended doses,
that could present
up to 75 times
the tolerable daily intake.
When those two off-the-charts
contaminated brands
were tested in the 2018 survey,
they only had down
about the limit.
This confirms
that there is a potential
for great variability
between lots of AFA
harvested from Klamath Lake.
So even if a supplement company
claims their brand
tested under the limit,
you never know
what their next bottle
is going to contain.
Other studies have shown up to
the same 50-fold variability
among batches
of the very same brand.
There was even a case reported
of a young woman
who died of liver failure
tentatively attributed
to the prolonged consumption
of toxic AFA supplements,
given the levels of the toxins
the researchers
were able to pick up
in the liver on autopsy.
In light of the findings,
the distribution
and commercial sales
of AFA blue-green algae products
for human consumption
appear highly questionable.
And the irony is that
they are commonly consumed
for purported "detoxification."
Here's the latest:
2023, Klamath Lake AFA
continues to be contaminated
with up to ten times
the upper safety limit.
To minimize exposure
to these toxins,
the researchers suggest
using spirulina
or chlorella-based products
instead.
But are they any safer?
We'll find out next.
Previously I've talked about
chlorella's potential benefits
for preserving
the immune function of athletes
and improving some
cardiovascular risk factors,
such as dropping blood pressures
by a few points
or lowering LDL cholesterol
about eight points.
Remember that green eggs
and ham study,
where taking chlorella
with eggs
appeared to blunt
the rise in cholesterol?
It may help detoxify
some dietary cholesterol,
but what about the toxins
found contaminating
many algae supplements?
Blue-green algae like AFA
can make their own toxins,
but even if the green algae
chlorella can't,
when chlorella
is skimmed off the ponds,
the presence of other algae
and microorganisms
is unavoidable
and can pose a hazard.
When you actually look
at commercial algae supplements
under a microscope,
the provided labels
are usually inaccurate
as factual contents
usually do not match.
They may be contaminated
with fungus,
other algae and bacteria,
and it seems the contamination
was more frequent
in the organic
versus conventional products.
One product advertised
as 100 percent organic chlorella
contained both liver toxins
and neurotoxins.
I've talked
about a case report
of apparent
chlorella-induced psychosis.
There's also been a case
of kidney damage reported
as well as an apparent
chlorella-induced drop
in platelet count.
Some reactions
are hard to miss,
like a whole-body rash
or nausea, headache,
dizziness, fatigue,
abdominal pain,
and general weakness
that rapidly resolved
after stopping.
In these cases, though,
it was a mixed algae product.
Even without contamination,
if you cultivate pure chlorella
it can still significantly
induce DNA damage
in human cells.
Yeah, but those are all cells
in a petri dish.
Yes, but they were
colon lining cells,
so cells presumably exposed
directly to chlorella
when you eat it.
Though chlorella has been
marketed for "detoxification,"
it can be contaminated
with toxin-producing algae
and end up exceeding
safety limits.
For more irony,
chlorella can sometimes
be contaminated in a good way.
Chlorella species
can't make vitamin B12,
but they may mix with
B12-synthesizing bacteria,
such that if you give chlorella
to some vegetarians and vegans
with a suspected
vitamin B12 deficiency,
most seem to get
a little improvement
in their B12-status.
But after two months
of supplementation,
they were still,
on average, deficient.
Note that chlorella is not
considered to be a reliable,
sufficient source
of vitamin B12.
The same with spirulina,
which was once thought
to contain B12,
but it's actually
mostly pseudo-B12,
a form of B12
unusable by humans
and therefore
not a suitable B12 source.
What about spirulina
as a source of toxins?
I'll address
just that question next.
Spirulina is
a microscopic blue-green algae
whose carotenoid pigments
are responsible
for the orange-pink hue
of flamingos.
At high enough doses
it can also turn us orange too,
like if we eat
too many carrots,
but it's considered benign
and goes away on its own
when you cut back.
The strangest color change
I ran across was this:
"Green Breast Milk
Following Ingestion
of Blue-Green Algae."
Whoa!
But thankfully that also
disappears after stopping.
Spirulina is said to have
various promising
health effects.
At the same time,
on the contrasting note,
there are toxins
that might contribute
to acute poisoning,
cancer, liver damage,
and gastrointestinal
disturbances,
with long-term consumption
potentially leading
to Alzheimer's
and Parkinson's disease.
Okay then.
And those purported
promised health effects,
like playing "a positive role
in treating muscle cramps"
are based on a study
in which mice were injected
with formaldehyde and vinegar.
What can spirulina
actually do in people?
Spirulina can improve
long-term blood sugar control
in rats, but, apparently,
not in humans.
It's also disappointing
when it comes
to anti-inflammatory
or antioxidant effects.
Spirulina may help
lower cholesterol, though,
perhaps due
to reducing fat absorption
and lower blood pressures
by four or five points.
There was a recent trial
where mild-to-moderate
Alzheimer's patients
were randomized
to a gram a day
of spirulina or placebo
for 12 weeks,
and appeared to end up
slightly better off cognitively
than those
in the control group.
So those are some
of the potential upsides.
The concern is that,
although algae supplements
like blue-green algae,
chlorella, and spirulina
are all advertised
as being beneficial,
they might be harmful
because they may contain
algal toxins.
Though most toxins are found
contaminating the Klamath Lake
AFA blue-green algae,
some toxins are found in some
spirulina supplements as well.
Spirulina samples tested
from markets around the world
have shown
highly variable results,
ranging from non-detection
to alarming levels of toxins.
The presence of toxin-producing
algae contaminants
is the most likely explanation
for the presence of toxins
in spirulina products,
because producers
cultivate spirulina
in open outdoor ponds
which are vulnerable
to contamination
with toxin-producing species.
There have been calls
for strict quality control
and monitoring,
but that doesn't seem
to have panned out.
This study examined
what was growing
in five commercial
spirulina products
including pills and powders.
Several potentially
pathogenic bacteria
were detected
in the products,
and algae toxins were found
in all of the products
at levels that could lead
to consumers exceeding
the recommended daily limits.
One study of five
protein powders with spirulina
found that four of them
even contained BMAA,
which is a neurotoxin
linked to some progressive
neurodegenerative diseases
like ALS,
which I've talked about before.
Yet spirulina products
continue to be advertised
as detoxifiers.
Though spirulina
is commonly contaminated,
the levels of toxins
is significantly lower
than has been found in other
blue-green algae supplements.
Nevertheless, there's a concern
that long-term exposure
to even very low levels
of these toxins
may increase the risk
of liver cancer, for example.
There are also case reports
of acute liver damage
tentatively tied
to spirulina intake,
as well as acute muscle damage
and rare autoimmune reactions
to spirulina,
AFA blue-green algae, or both,
including blistering disorders
too disturbing to display.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest major book,
“How Not to Age” is out.
Check it out from your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books
go to charity.
I actually just came out
with another small book:
an easy 100-page read on
Ozempic and other GLP-1 drugs.
Go to NutritionFacts.org
and click on “Books”
to see where you can get an e-book,
audiobook, or paperback of it.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There are no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.